Amsterdam is facing one of the worst
housing crises in Europe.  Despite being
fetishized by like one or two YouTube
channels, the city has a dirty secret.
Waiting list longer than a decade for
social housing.  An average home price of
over 600,000 [music]
and rising.  Medi private r the highest
in Europe.  And the strangest part is
that Amsterdam was once a world leader
at housing.  Like Vienna nearly 40% of
housing [music] stock is publicly
funded affordable housing.  So how can
hous [music] crisis be so bad?
This is a story about why Amsterdam is
slowly becoming a dystopia.  A system
that showers rewards on insiders who are
able to get in on time [music]
while being completely unaffordable to
people and newers.  Thankfully, municipal
elections are coming up on March 18th
[music]
so might finally change and I thought
wouldn't it be fun to invite Amsterdam's
four biggest political parties for an
interview to ask them [music] some
questions I reached out to the green
left party the party for labor.  D66 VVD
[music]
brightest housing policy experts and for
some reason they all accepted
[music]
myself.
You want to stay anonymous, so that's
great, man.  You say I want
[music] more regulation now, but I remain
anonymous.  Good role, huh.  [laughter]
Instead, I had to find someone who could
be uniquely [music] irritating.
Matsmeus is a friend from the line of
kids pick last in gym class.  While some
people [music] are gifted at sports,
music or math, Mats is gifted at being
annoying.
We want as many people as possible to be
able to own a home, but we
also want those homes to always
continue to rise in value.  So it will become more expensive
.
Yes,
it's a bit hard to reconcile, is
n't it?  Ultimately,
rent regulation is perhaps a good
topic to
discuss in a bit more detail.  You are a big
supporter of that.   Of
course.  Yes, 1000%.
1000%.  But generally speaking,
rent regulation is also something that
most [music] economists say: "That is
not the wisest way to deal with your
rental market. You are, you are an
alderman. Uh, and you are elected by the right to
vote in Amsterdam. What gives
someone who was born in Amsterdam more
right to the city than someone who was not
born in Amsterdam?"
Uh, and he said about
Rob Jette's 10 new cities plan that it is the
D6 voters who will be the first to block it
.  And I thought that was a really
funny one, but I mean, that does
n't really matter.  So I thought it would be
funny to get him to interview a bunch
of Amsterdams.
Isn't it fair to say that we,
as a left-wing municipality in a right
-wing country, must relate to this policy?
By becoming more right-wing.  And we invited
all the living room with a cameraman.   Yes yes yes yes
.  You wanted to make it very technical,
so I I I I do my best.
[music]
Spending €130 million on 2,000
underground parking spaces.
And this is a sort of social rent
for parking spaces.  And generations for
the city.
Too little is being built [music], there is too
little movement within the housing market, and first-time buyers can hardly
find suitable homes.
Houses are becoming less affordable at a very rapid pace
.  But is there anything other than
hope for leadership?  In a way that does
n't come down to, well, we just keep
going to The Hague.
This is a story of why Amsterdam doesn't
know how to build.
Affordable Rent Act  Uh, that [music]
really helped a lot in Amsterdam.
You look at what the law has done, and
it has led the city to more
owner-occupied homes and wealthier people.
Both national and local.  [music] do
you still find it difficult to
criticize that rent regulation?
Yes, it is a nuanced
story.
Certainly.
[music]
Right, we’ll discuss that
with Mark Rutte, the VVD’s lead candidate, in a moment
.
Bram Bitterman is a 22-year-old university
student living in his parents
apartment.
He just got kicked out of his private
sector rental unit.  His parents are
divorced, but his dad sleeps in the
kitchen because he can't find a new
place to live.
Brom is lonely.  Hisone is ofer matches
that he doesn't tell he lives with his
mother.  [music]
The walls in his apartment are thin.  He
can he nebors at
politicians on TV endless grandims about
solving housing.  Why does he feel like
it only keeps getting worse?
Amsterdam's housing system used to be a
point of national pride.  [music] Today
it's a high stakes competition where the
losers end up in permanent.  And that's
because Amsterdam housing market is one
of the strangest in the world.  [music]
It combines some of the worst parts of
European socialist systems with the
worst parts of the market systems.
[music]
To understand how possible, we have to
go back.
In the late [music] 1800s, Amsterdam
was growing at break speed.
Industrialization meant that peasants
[music] moved to the city on mass to
take factory jobs.  They were dirt poor
and rented rooms in slums like the
Jordan.  The conditions were horrible.
Po health, high density and bad
sanitation [music]
disease and disorder disaster and housing
was completely unreulated two [music]
families of sleeping in a single
basement room was unheard of the canals
[music] open seers.
So in 1901 the government intervened
with the voting vet the housing act the
Netherlands [music] first ever housing
regulation establish strict building
codes local governments [music] their
own building ordinances with CI creating
their own codes technical standards
[music] minimum room heights adequate
daylight penetration and ventilation
it also provided the financial [music]
framework for housing association ring
corporations to build at scale.  Voting
corporates are a [music] unique part of
the Dutch system.  In contrast to
countries like Russia and the US, the
Dutch government never built [music]
much housing.  Instead, it paid
independent nonprofit associations
[music] to build for their members.
Teachers, Catholics and socialists all
had their own [music] corporations.
But in 1939, the second world war broke
out.  The country's housing stock
[music] was devastated.
After the war, the nation faced a new
crisis.  The combination of a baby boom
of a massive supply shortage [music]
caused the greatest housing crisis of
all time.  So the state doubled down not
by [music] giving the market free as
the Americans did but by establishing
essentially a socialist system.  Central
planning [music]
ample state funding spare rooms were
confiscated moving to a new city
required a permit.  There was even a
special tax on being single.
In Amsterdam, the general expansion plan
was implemented.  It created the garden
cities in Amsterdam's west and north.
The houses there were rental homes built
by the voting corporations and subsidized
heavily by the government.  Between 1945
and 1970 social housing built mostly by
vingories expanded to nearly 40% of the
city's total stock.  It's hard to
understand how different this period
was.  There was no private rental market.
Home ownership was for people.  The
national government decided what was
built, paid for it, and set what they
thought was a fair rent.  But then
something changed.
For what it's [music] worth, Brum's
parents were happy while last.  They
lived in social housing, [music] only a
month for a two bedroom apartment in the
pipe.  The city's trendiest neighborhood,
increasingly filled with consultants and
developers.
His parents got the apartment many years
ago and they have a permanent contract.
As long as they don't start a lab, they
can never get kicked out.  It's a
beautiful system, Brom.  A decent
apartment with low rent for working
people
washing dishes for an hour also makes
him a working person.
Why is there no art for him in the he
grew up in?  Why does his dad have to
sleep in his kitchen?  He goes online
looking for information something can
explain why this system isn't working.
By the 1960s, trucking and trains meant
that heavy industry could leave cities.
Mass car ownership meant that growing
middle classes could live further away
from their work.  Dutch society
suburbanized.
They left their cramp departments for
houses with gardens.  People didn't need
to live in Amsterdam anymore, so they did
n't.  Amsterdam population dining house
prices came down because property values
decline
make final anymore.  Historic canal
homesollapsed into the mud.  There was
less tax income garbage pickup and road
maintenance became unaffordable.  More
people left.  Property values ​​declined
even more.  It looked like the city in
the age of the car was doomed.
That same pattern occurred across the
great cities of the western world a
postw housing crisis an exodus from the
city leading to urban blight.  After the
war, the urban working classes began
[music] to move to greener pastures.
Prices came down which helped new people
move in.  students [music] artist
bohemians
declining spending bad economy also
social unrest [music]
crime drugs andapidation
the amsterdam as population declined the
city center decayed abandoned buildings
taken over [music] by squatters who
frequently clash with the police a
heroin epidemic swept the city [music]
burglares and street crime on the rise
amsterdam's government embarked in
ambitious project of urban
[music]
housing fixed funds and rented [music]
out for fair price
municipal councelorfer dispossessed
private landlords and did everything in
his  power to get more funding from the
central government and st worked in 1985
amstam's population began to grow again
and grow and grow on the national level
housing policy was going through radical
change the second world
ta money
housing standards paid constructions
[music] and decided how high the rent
could be public spending on construction
was massive between 1970 and 1986 it
rose from3% to 2% of GDP today that
would be around [music] 24 billion
euros per year housing wasn't actually
built by the government it  was built by
the corporate
government could  only nudge them As
non-profits, they had an incentive to
[music] spend as much on construction
as they could.  That meant the Ministry
of Housing had to set increasingly
stringent construction rules.  They
decided exactly what [music] kind of
materials a countertop should be made of
and what the maximum number of square
meters for a shower was.  [music]
Meanwhile, nearly a 30 of people living
in public housing were high income.  The
government subsidized their homes for
billions [music] a year.
So in 1989 ministerma
presented the memorandum housing
[music] in 90s the government was to
take a step back from housing policy
corporates going to be responsible for
their own finances [music] for the
first time rent control was removed from
the most expensive part of the market
the position of ving corporations within
the Dutch system kept getting weirder
[music] they had to house the poor but
they also had to make their own money
with investments they had to administer
billions worth of housing stock [music]
run with the
[music]
FR was
home
public housing.  A problem since the war
.  Too little [music] is being
built, there is too little movement, and
first-time buyers can hardly
find suitable houses [music].
Independence build.  Right, we'll talk about that in a moment
.  With Mark Rutte, the
lead candidate of [music] the VVD, with
Mark Jan Aen of the Eigenhuis association
and with Peter Boelhouer, professor of
[music] housing at the TU in Delft.
Keeping rents low is always popular, but
low rent means there's less money for
building and maintenance.  In the old
days, the government at least
compensated for low [music] rents with
increased subsidies.  Now they lower the
rent and say that someone will find
money to build.
The problem is, look, the problem is
that the government has had to reconsider housing over the past four
years.  At
the same time inspired by Great Britain,
the Netherlands wanted to promote home
ownership.  They did that allowing
corporations parts their [music] stock.
But what do you want then?  What we want are
cooperatives. What we want now is to
force them, really force them, uh, with a levy,
to sell at least 1% per year of a housing portfolio [music].
I cannot imagine that the
premise that the VVD
wants to skim off 3.5 billion from housing corporations in
favor of tax relief
really makes the corporation eager to
do that.  Actually, if we
all want more homes to be
built, you should say that
money needs to be invested in the
housing market.  Not me.  They also let
potential home buyers borrow absurd
amounts of money relative to their
incomes and made it much more
financially attractive than renting in
practical cases.  I want to take the
boohouder a step further.  Uh, you would
also say that [music] uh the
mortgage interest deduction
makes it easier for people to
buy a house [music].
Why is that apparently not the case, then?
Well, that is that is very simple because uh
the mortgage [music] has afd that is
a demand stimulus right.  That gives you
more purchasing power.  But because the
supply is indeed not being realized [music]
, yes, you see that
reflected directly in rising prices.  It
's a bit of a game of leapfrog, isn't it?  [music]
If you look at our neighboring countries,
Belgium and Germany, they don't have that
system, do they?  They have done that very
wisely, by the way.  They abolished that,
and then you see that the prices
are already a third lower than
ours.
So that is [music],
it is bad for house prices.  It is
driving up house prices.
Well, it certainly drives up house prices
.  A tradition of midwalt began.
We, as the VVD, advocate for
more people owning their own homes.
That the number of people with their
own homes will increase.  What
I also find remarkable is that, for
example, a party like
Tetcher's in England in 1979, based on
liberal ideology,
slowly
phased out the mortgage limits.  [music] Namely
freedom of choice.  You don't, uh, force people in
a certain direction through the state, as it were
.  So [music],
I find that very remarkable.  A land trap
was set in motion.  So that means that
soon you will have a lot of [music] people in the Netherlands who own a house that
is worth less than the
outstanding mortgage.  And that is in my
absolute conviction [music] has far-reaching
consequences for the economy, quite apart from
the trust that is violated between citizen and
government.  Namely that
[music] people thought they could count on
long-term certainty.  Housing became the
primary vehicle for future building.
[music]
Defunded housing corporations and
subsidized homeownership divided the
population.  Renters who had hustled
their way into a good contract had no
reason to leave.  Perspective renters
kept out by long waiting lists or sky
high [music] rents.  Home owners who had
bought their way in on time, profited
from inflated home prices.  Perspective
homeowners competed for housing that
became less access year.  By the 2000
touches were interest onlyan
pay down your debt.   Are
we plunging people into massive
debt?  Uh, the Netherlands is uh above
mortgage debt uh uh compared
to America.  You shouldn't want that.  And uh
moreover, the uh
mortgage interest deduction uh instrument is not
effective in
promoting home ownership.  It only drives
up house prices, and first-time buyers
essentially hand over an entire mortgage interest deduction directly to the homeowner.
House prices rose pocket the difference
if they could be left with tens of
thousands of euros in debt.
I find it insane, then, that you, as a
liberal, defend this measure.  It does
not do what you think it does.  And
we all have to pay 5% more tax across the
board on our income
.
Yes, because that is the big problem,
you say.  It just costs a lot of
money.  And moreover, we have
plunged ourselves up to our necks in debt with 600
billion in mortgage debt.
Yes, the economy is therefore very
vulnerable to risks.
Why?  What can happen?  Well, at the
moment that is... so we are working, when
the economy is doing well, on strengthening the results in the
Dutch economy
by stimulating demand for houses through fiscal means
.  And as a result,
the housing market goes boom, uh, gets amplified.
And if it goes down, we are once again,
uh, reinforcing the economic downturn
with, uh, the
government's fiscally driven instrument.  So we are
breathing extra financial risk through the mortgage interest deduction
.  Property values
dropped and hundreds of thousands of
households suddenly had more debt than
their houses were worth.  The government
[music] understandably had to fix that.
They couldn't afford to let home owners
go broke.  Even though property values
have been kept artificially high, home
prices had to rise again to prevent a
wave of bankruptcies.
Housing minister Step Blook unleashed
the animal spirits of the market on the
rental sector.  Not lenders but investors
would prop up prices this time around a
new tax was leved on ving corpora theers
heing the landlords levy.  This forced
them to sell big parts of their stock to
investors.  It also prevented them from
investing in new housing and maintenance
[music] and European competition rules
meant that voting cooperatives had to
disinvest from the more expensive
[music] part of the market where rents
were higher.  This greatly worsen their
financial position.
While St deregulated the demand side of
the housing market, the supply side was
left unchanged.  It was [music] induced
demand on a massive scale.
By 2017, the government believed the
market finally stabilized [music] and
the position of minister of housing was
abolished.  There was no need for it
anymore.  The minister said the housing
market was complete.  That turned out to
be a little bit premature.
The reason Amsterdam is so expensive is
because it's a great place to be.  The
best jobs, areas and opportunities
[music]
are all concentrated in a few square
kilometers of swamp.  That means
homeowners sit on monopoly positions.
The supply of land is fixed.  [music]
You either pay up or you leave.  Access
to work in others is so high and demand
so rents can be extractive.  But what if
it didn't have to be?  Any desk is a
remote desktop app.  [music] It's a
European company which today is
something I value more than any time
before.  It lets you access and control
any computer from anywhere with basically
no lag.  Their proprietary codec makes it
feel like [music] you're sitting right in
front of the machine.  This means you
can arbitrage, put your workstation in a
different city where rent is a third of
the price and operate it from a cafe on
the canals.  You get all the network
effects of a [music] major city but
none of the monop rent for your office
space.  It works across every platform.
[music]
Windows, Mac, Linux, even your phone.
It's encrypted endto-end with banking
great security, hundreds of millions of
downloads, trusted by Fortune 500
companies and freelancers and overprice
departments alike.  If Amsterdam's
housing market won't let you in, any
desk lets you cheat.  Check it out for
free at anyesk.com/hook.
Link in the description.
Through the Amsterdam popular economy
attracted more people.
The cycle of decline that the doors of
the 80s have predicted did not come
true.  In fact, highly [music] educated
CI like Amsterdam proved to be even more
important.  Aglomeration effects,
benefits from workers being close
together growth.  The best [music] jobs,
companies and universities in Europe
here.  Old socialist like had a much
easier job.  They had to fix housing at a
time when demand [music] was falling.
But these days everyone wants to live in
Amsterdam.  When demand drops, [music]
house prices won't rise either.
But Amsterdam boom so hard that supply
[music] wasn't able to keep up.  In
2017, Amsterdam implemented the 40420
rule.  40% of new builds to be social
housing, 40% midmket [music] rent and
20% market rate.  The problem was that
rents in the social housing and sectors
were kept far too low [music] for
projects to break even.  And unlike in
the 80s, the central government has to
make out for the difference with
subsidies.
tax on citizens highable
house [music]
market
on that [music] uh uh yeah
rigid percentages huh 40 40 20
40% social 40% middle and 20% free
sector.  That you then, um, uh, that you
actually [musically] corner yourself as a city.  uh
that you build fewer homes and have more
money left over for the amenities that are of
course also important for
[music] a uh total complete city.
Especially because construction also
kept getting more expensive.  The
financial crisis in COVID causes many
construction workers to [music] leave
the industry.  At the same time,
environmental regulations got stricter.
Inflation meant that wages and material
went up while regulated [music] rents
didn't.  Highboring costs brought up the
total cost for housing development.  And
Amsterdam's municipal government kept
piling on additional requirements.
We are basically saying that you need to be social 40% of the time and
in the middle 40%.  Well, that
is the entire area
for a
developer to extract returns from, for the one who is going to
build.  That is actually not possible with the
normal land prices that Amsterdam
[music] charges.  So that has to be
cheaper.  Well, then all sorts of
sustainability requirements are thrown on top of that
.  And all sorts of other requirements
for accessibility as well.  And well,
some are quite logical, but I think that
enormous accumulation of requirements [music]
ultimately causes a
developer to look at it and say: "Yes, we
are going to build homes now, but we are making a
loss on it."  Which is actually hard to
imagine with those square prices
you're mentioning, but it is true nonetheless.
But how is that, how is that, how did
that come about?
Because everyone has their own
wish list.  So everyone on the
city council has their own
wish list.  What requirements must such a building
meet, then?  Then someone comes along again and
says: "Well, wouldn't it
be nice if we could also
let all sorts of horizontal greenery [music] or something grow along the buildings. Parking,
huh. Well, well, parking. No, certainly. But it
also makes it more complicated. You're
right about that.
That those homes are climate-proof
[music]. So insulate well and
also make sure that, well, we see that problem a
lot now, that roofs that aren't eh
insulated eh or for example
aren't um covered with a green
roof. Yeah, people are sitting there
panting themselves completely [music] in the
summer. Um, so we actually need to
prepare those existing homes for the
future. The nice thing about
housing associations is that you can tell
them to do whatever you want and you
don't actually have to pay.
And how it works in the Netherlands is that we are
constantly asking all kinds of things of
associations. And the associations
themselves are a bit timid types
walking around there. So they
actually never say well, but they say
very little. They say very little
to the municipality like, hey guys, uh,
those  sustainability requirements that all those
monuments we have to maintain in
the city center.
No, I really do get this this this
back from cooperatives that actually put this
[music] well, matter on the
table. And I also think we
need to enter into dialogue with them about that.
How do you ensure that the financial
position [music]
uh well, better uh uh becomes than it
is now?
Well, the land price in Amsterdam is
about €5000 per square meter. Look, a
parking space is 20. Uh so if you
calculate that uh then a
parking space costs
€100,000
one parking space.
Yes. And
if you uh if you
want to get a somewhat healthy return on that
, then uh that is a rental price of
uh €3000 [music] per year. That would be fair
. Yes, I
But you pay 385.
Yes,
so that is actually a [music]
subsidy, right, of about 90%.
Well, partly I think so.
Building cost for social housing
increase from 55 [music]  to
47 people
between 2018 and 2023. That's a
lot.
What I think my question is more? Um
look, you could, for example,
say uh
you have uh well, so you have the replacement
fund that is uh
getting smaller and smaller. You have the national
government amounts just not going up. Uh
so you have all uh the corporations
that are slowly going bankrupt.
Yes. No. Yes. No, you have to make choices, right?
So that's why...
But what are... Because is it
sustainability then? Is it double glazing? Is
it uh okay, we might
sell a few more monuments. Uh what what is
the priority? So, people people what does that
mean
and then just on the cost side, right, because
I think on the revenue side I thought, well
if you ultimately
can't make it work with cuts then
maybe you could possibly look at taxes
. [music] Um and I think
on the cost side it is really
about helping those most vulnerable people that
you put that first. And not everything costs
money either of course, right. So the  regulating
where we have done what we have done which, um,
also, uh, many slum landlords are really
angry about. Yes, but yes, that, uh, did
n't cost us that much except for
bureaucratic effort.
But at the same time, I really think we
need to move away from "oh yeah, how
much does that cost then and how much does that cost
then?" Because in itself, we do that:
looking at every dossier to see what you want and what it
costs approximately, and then bringing that closer to
each other. [music] But that
regulation
actually seems almost taboo with a lot of
parties, like with centrist parties, because
of "oh no, because
then we'll scare
away investors, for example." Yes, and I
just think that's the world turned upside down. The rise in
building costs were partially caused by
environmental rules. Climate change is
one of the biggest challenges facing
humanity. So wanting construction to be
green makes sense. But there's something
paradoxical about green building
[music] rules in cities. Urban living
already lowers carbon footprints
dramatically. People use public
transport instead of driving cars. They
live in smaller spaces and use less
energy. So the weird thing is that
almost everything that's more people live
in cities is good for the environment.
includes scrapping some environmental
rules to build more housing in the end a
simple question of addition and
subtractions and revenues it can decide
to subsidize building with tax revenue or
can landlords charge high rent but what
it can't do is have everything all at
once low rent low subsidies and circular
building rules for midrent housing that
also needs to fund affordable housing
luckily most people understand that
intuitively but there's one minister
that
room
expive
ching
for student roomalor
years br signed upent
00 a month fory room apartment building
brally freed from his parents  and he was
having time of his life for br spending
half the salary he made a dishwer on a
room made
[music]
Moning life horable
acted out of his house his landlord sold
the building to a yppie.
Bram went back to his parents.
Hugo de Jonges Affordable Rent Act,
Affordable Rent Act is a perfect example
of noble [music] intentions being led
by failing to think through the
consequences.
Voting against a law that everyone
pretends will lower the rent is a great
way to lose an election.  The idea behind
the law was simple enough.  Landlords
Shouldn't be able to overcharge for
shitty homes to set a fair rent in the social
sector. The government uses a point
system to determine how attractive a house
is. The system regulates rents up to a
certain number of points, so the market
gets to set its own price. An elevator or
more floor size gives you extra points.
Poor insulation makes you lose them. The number
of points a house receives
determines its fair rent. Elegant system
[music] designed to incense high-quality
housing. Systems apply to pre-conform
[music]. A system designed
on the canal ramp in the city center is worth
less than a terrorist house of alma mater. But
if there's one thing landlords and
renters look for in real estate more
than anything else, it's location, location, location.
It's the reason a moldy old
canal house in Amstel City Center costs
10 times as much
[music].
It is actually the case that if you were to leave it to the market
[music], you could argue
that living within the ring or in the
city center would
actually be impossible for social housing. But that
choice was made at some point. So we
offered the possibility to live next to a
canal house that is somewhat on this
is currently worth millions, and there are still
social housing units available. Yes, if you
reason from the perspective that it’s all
unaffordable and we shouldn’t make that choice
, because the market will, uh,
eventually regulate, then
we would never have been able to hold onto these types of homes
. So I am very
happy that we did do that.
It caused rents in precisely those cute
[music] small, centrally located
apartments to drop dramatically. Rich
[ __ ] landlords being forced to lower
[music] the rent sounds like a fine
idea, but they still respond to
incentives and money follows the path of
[music] least resistance. While the
government applied strict rent control
to much of the rental market, they were still
allowed to sell their properties for the
market price. They did exactly that.
But I mean concretely, uh, it does look like it,
as we just discussed,
that
the affordable rent has reduced the supply in the
free rental sector.
Yes. So it has simply ensured, so to speak,
especially the homes that were a
bit [music] well, in the middle
of how attractive it is. Although
I also recently heard from a landlord  who
[music] had kicked out six students
because he preferred to sell. Well,
you can really make quite a bit of money on six students,
even if your [music] house
is expensive. Um, but a lot has been sold, and
that isn't... the story has been
told to me very one-sidedly since they
say, "Yeah, there's no more money to be
made [music] uh... with renting." Well, I do
n't think they can
get the return they used to have anymore
. So there isn't 7% on it anymore, but
for example 3%, right? And I think, well,
then you're still a lucky one,
because if we all put our money in the
savings bank, you get 1% now, I think
.
Yeah. And so if you give them a reason
that there is no money to be made in Oud
Zuid and there is a lot of money to be made
in a uh... less nice neighborhood of Hengelo, well, then
I suspect the money
flows to Hengelo.
And is it bad then that if, as a set,
that they... uh... that they...
sell their rental homes in Amsterdam... that
the whole free market sector is actually... well,
almost disappearing? What is actually
the problem with that?
Also  What we are seeing reflected now in the land
registry figures is that a lot of young first-time
buyers who previously simply didn't stand a chance in
Amsterdam—well, the place we were just talking about—
because it's
unaffordable, are now occasionally
getting a chance. So, I also hear
people saying about that: "Yeah, you know, I
get it."  Those investors aren't very
happy, because this is, well, this is how they
make their money.  Uh, but on the
other hand, we are now helping young people
who can afford it to
get onto the housing market.
The people who lost their private sector
rental homes were
generally poorer.  Uh, so those had to come out.
Those who have left their homes.  They
have often left the city.  Hmm hmm.
So this is a procedure.  I mean,
everyone understands that those rents were too high
, but it's like you look at
what sort of in the real world
[music] uh
the law has done.  has led to
more owner-occupied homes and wealthier people.
Yes, I think what is wrong there is the
analysis of what is happening now with
mid-market rent.  Because of course, yes,
if your home has a number of points,
then it now falls into the mid-market rent category.  So
for all those people living in those homes
, the city actually becomes much more
affordable.  And I think, yeah, what I said
[music], that I just think the private sector is
a really bad
invention anyway.
Well, if you say that it is fantastic
that people should own homes in
the center of Amsterdam, then of course it is
no problem.  Yes,
because if a lot of rental homes
are sold, you get more
owner-occupied homes.
Um, and then living in Amsterdam, uh yeah, there are a
lot of people who live in owner-occupied houses.
The other side of the story is,
of course, that then you won't have any
rental homes there anymore.  Currently, it is
generally the case that tenants do not
have the budget for dormitories, so they simply have to
live somewhere else.  The people who bought their
houses were happy, but they were a much
richer group than Bram and [music] his
friends.  They were left empty-handed.
Not enough time on the winning list for
social [music] housing, not nearly
enough money to buy a house.  A law that
was meant to lower their rent by a
little bit ended up lowering it to zero.
The sector they were dependent on had
disappeared.
And so I am going to, uh, sell my house.
[music] So what are you going to see?  You are going to
see the shift from a rental market to an owner
-occupied market.  We've also seen in the past eh
period, haven't we, that there was actually quite a bit of [music] on
offer,
especially for beginners.
Um,
those are really rich first-time buyers, right?
Because the average
house price in Amsterdam is, uh, €700,000,
I believe.
Yeah, that is uh
so that is not uh bill [music]
guitar.  No, and but it is it is absolutely
true that the uh prices are rising, but the
[music] they have therefore risen less sharply
than if uh this uh piece of
supply were not there.
But I mean those who are first-time buyers on the
housing market have, on average,
twice as high an income
as the renters in the private sector.  So
that is, well, I mean, it is yet another
shift towards a much wealthier group of
people, right?
Yes, I think that varies a bit.
And I think that one of the most complicated
things is what you actually
point out as well, that a lot of people
in that private sector are stuck right now.  They pay way too
much.  In Amsterdam, that's 17%
[music]
of tenants in the private sector who
pay much more rent relative to
their income than is actually okay,
right?  So if, on top of that, you also
want to enroll your child in a sport, and yes, you
still have the electricity bill and so on
that you have to pay as well, there are
quite a lot of people
struggling there.  [music] And that is why I
also think that you should regulate all rents again
, because the private rental
sector is what everyone [music] can
afford to depend on and is shrinking.  With
limited supply, there are only two ways
to divide up existing housing.  High
prices or rent control with waiting
lists.  High prices pull cash into
construction.  But drive up living costs.
Rent control keeps things affordable for
insiders, [music] but shrink supply for
everyone else.  Landlords who can't make
the numbers work, sell.  The home still
exists, but now you need savings to live
in them.  The rental market shrinks.  The
buying market gets more competitive.  The
people with the lease capital get
squeezed out of both.
The reason why I
find this most worrying is that you
actually see that
we want to help first-time homebuyers in the Netherlands, and we do a
lot for them and spend quite a lot of
money.  Huh, all those tax measures,
mortgage interest deduction, not
paying transfer tax if you
're under 35.  Um, now we
all have first-time buyer systems
, right? We have incentives for first-time
buyers, you name it.  Quite a
lot of money goes towards that.  [music] But for the
people who cannot afford to buy a house,
we say: "Well, just join that
long waiting line for social housing."
You can see that the housing association stock is
barely growing, and that
rent freeze won't change that either.  If
investors just have to fill the gap then,
because out of sheer desperation those people have no better
alternative than [music], right,
renting one of those investor properties that is much more expensive
.  Then we say no; we should
n't want that either.   Yes.
If rising prices means there's more
demand supply then why isn't supply
increasing?  Because restrictive
construction is a choice.  Protecting low
density postal housing from deterioration
is a choice.  Not building on farmland
of the city is a choice.  None of this is
a fact of nature.
Social housing in Amsterdam shows what
happens when you try to fix supply
problem with a price ceiling and a
national government that doesn't
subsidize construction [music] and
taxes roing corporates.  You get waiting
list for social housing that are over 10
years.
Luckily, the Amsterdam City Council has
for years had a trick up on its sleeve.
The booming city meant that companies
wanted to move there, rich companies,
and they all wanted big offices.  And for
reasons beyond the scope of this video,
[music] Amstam's municipal government
is the owner of most of the city's land.
That means it can charge rich companies
a lot of money to use their land.  The
city's massive land profits were put
into the
equalization fund.  Uh, and that was about the
equalization fund.  So, uh, maybe
it is good to briefly explain what
the equalization fund is.  [music]
No, what we do is we build uh uh
homes in our city.  We don't do that
ourselves.
Project developers [music] often do that,
and they make a contribution when it comes to
building the more expensive homes,
and those then go into a fund.  And with
that fund, we can, uh, well, finance the
social [music] rental homes
.  But that's not all.  You
also need to make other investments.   For
example, preparing
land for construction.  [music]
Um ensures that there is also mobility
present in a uh in Wijkenaar.  And
that fund is called the peat extraction fund.
With that fund, the local government can
do what the national government did in
the 80s.  [music] Subsidize land for
rent-controlled construction.  It's a
neat system.  You extract land rent and
use that money to fund housing that's
accessible to all income groups.  There's
one catch, though.  If more people want to
live in the city, you need to keep the
land profits coming, [music] which
means you need to rent out more and more
land to rich developers.  In recent
years, most of that land was on the ZOS.
Amsterdam's [music] fancy new business
district.  But now the outas the Dutch
Wall Street is full and politicians keep
moving money fund to the general budget.   Well, uh,
the equalization fund is
indeed, isn't it? It's actually expensive projects; the ones
we make a profit on pay for the
projects that cost money.  Only in
Amsterdam has that gone too far.  So what
you see is that actually that whole jar
is empty.  There is no money left in it.
In fact, it is so empty that for the
next 10 to 15 years—the
prediction is no—if we
continue as we are now, we won't be
able to identify any more loss-making projects.  Well, that simply means
that we won't be able to build a huge number of homes
anymore if we can't
secure projects.
Um, how is it that VVONs always
fills up?  That is due to those expensive
projects.  So those luxury homes
ensure that a lot of money
comes in, and with that you can
build social housing [music].
Yes, if you ensure that all those luxury
projects or all those somewhat more expensive
homes and private sector properties are
no longer built,
no money will come into the coffers.  So you ca
n't build a social structure either.  And that is what has
happened now.
Meanwhile, the number of projects
Amsterdam has to years growing.
Thousands of homes are infested with
mold.  They need to be renovated.
Amsterdam wants to switch cooking and
heating from gas to electricity.  We also
want green space, good roads, municipal
pools, cheap homes that are built as
green as possible.  And so that means
no more money for a swimming pool, no
more money for mobility, and no
more money for making
the existing homes more sustainable.  All this
is expensive can do enough money.
Nimbism
getting permits takes forever.  It
becomes impossible to predict how long a
building project takes and time is money.
Uncertainty scares off developers.
Amsterdam fundraisers.
Brum was sitting in cafe bells.  He was
with a friend who was unemployed, but
who always seemed to have an exact
answer for how the entire world should
be organized.  His friend said, "Bram,
they're always talking about building,
building, building."  And it's it's
really not that simple as building more.
He smirked and turned back to his flat
white and pretentious student magazine.
Brum was confused and then quiet for a
second.
seen before never underst
other friends YouTube videos narrators
ridiculous
never people building more
and so money to be made why did it still
so incredibly hard housing that was being
rented was sold to now home owners who
either wealthier or took on massive debt
and desperately needed their
rising
corporat
slowly going broke politicians
limit credit cards construction needs to
navigate layers of individually
reasonable rules that are collectively
paralying and pretty much everyone in
and outside the governments to vet
de veringsfonds the fund Amsterdam has
been using to fund new buildings and
affordability mandates is running  out.
The boredom fund, that is a fund of
hundreds of millions, those are really when you're talking
about Foxvesting, those are
always huge amounts and I think the
withdrawal amounted to uh
24, I think
24 million.
Yes, but that's not... they are
n't huge amounts either
if you, if you, if you look at the whole picture,
right?
No, but you... but again, that is why
I say it is a button.  Yes.
Um, it's not the holiest
button of all, but it is a button that I would
also say you should
[music] look at.  If you could
get a bit more breathing room in there,
you could also make the right choice at other tables and
other places
to arrive at, uh, building,
uh, ultimately [music] 80% affordable
rent.
But Amsterdam doesn't seem to have many
other levers and ways to increase
revenue.  Raising property taxes, despite
being a superior form of taxation
compared to income or taxes on business
is politically toxic.  Uh, and you need to look at that
too.  And the question is also whether
it is necessary, right? Because, well, you can
raise the property tax every time and collect the money from
the people of Amsterdam.  You can also look at
your own civil service, which is what we would like
.  Uh, which has also just
[music] thinned out by 20% over the past few years
.  Which has become totally inefficient,
uh, uh, instead of just going around
collecting taxes
from people again and again.
Uh but I [music] mean if you
if you uh you say it is high.  Well,
increased by 185%.  If you put that in an
international perspective,
I mean, for example, in
large parts of America, [music] that is
not exactly uh the Soviet Union, uh it lies uh well,
they call that property
tax there lies at 1%.   Yes.
So if you have a
million-dollar house, you pay €10,000 per year
or dollars per year.   Yes.
Gomers are too powerful as a group.  So
without new land more land rents are
difficult to raise.  Raising the tourist
tax could be promising.  But the big
picture is that the city will have to
solve the housing crisis within roughly
current budget.  Meanwhile, the national
won be providing that much extra funding
either.
Kind of, that was already a lot of
money for the national government.
Yes,
but if you want to do that as a local government
,
yes, they can go in
and on the right.  That just is
n't possible.
No, we can never do that alone.  But
at the same time...
But you do have to do it alone, right?   Yes.
Well, I think that was actually my
goal with the essay, which really
struck me.  I started, well, almost four
years ago now, as Alderman for
Public Housing.  I had absolutely no
experience with this file.  So I started
reading like crazy that summer, uh, when
we had just started, wondering how
this actually works.  [music] And what I've
seen in recent years is that weaving isn't getting
outside that market mindset anymore either.
That doesn't exactly blab about ambition when it
comes to public housing.  So, uh,
national coalition agreement.  No, so uh that
is mainly the municipality that
uh has to foot the bill for that
.  Uh, but yeah no,
and I stand by it.  We have, um, always made this choice in
this city from a historical
perspective.
And we can also make this choice
as a city, because we actually
have the means to make that choice
.  But they are political
choices that we have always made as a city,
and that we must continue to make
.  Because for me, it is not so much about
how to make it round.  It is also a
matter of principle.  How do you keep these
accessible as well?  And from that position,
you then reason backward to see where it costs
money and what it comes at the
expense of.  And I think we have to make that choice
.
The state of the debate is a bit
depressing.  The 80% affordable housing
mandate looks increasingly like an empty
promise.  It should be the goal but of
what?  When investors can get better
returns in stocks, why build new rental
units?  When landlords can get more
selling existing rentals as owner
occupied homes, why keep renting them
out at all?  Multiple projects that would
add new housing supply have been
stopped.  When no new units get built at
all, you're redistributing nothing.
[music] Meanwhile, those who stand in
homes in Amsterdam ironically just get
what if there was an obvious solution.
Land production is decreasing, which means
that there is increasingly less land
available for the municipality to
allocate to parties.
Owned land.  Yes.   Yes.
Eiburg was the last large piece of land
that we, uh, as a municipality, had as a location ourselves
.
Yes, if you look at the map of Amsterdam
, this is a bit of a personal
pet peeve of mine, but uh
I'm curious where you...
Yes, I sometimes go to Landelijk Noord
and then you cycle through there and
you see all kinds of cows.   Yes.
And then it smells like fertilizer.   Yes.
And then you think, I am 10, within a 10-
minute bike ride of Noord station.
A metro line in which we,
as a community, have invested €0.4 billion.
Why are those cows here?  And is
n't this a great place when it comes to
land production,
land allocation, isn't it
logical to say: "Hey, we're trying
to do everything within the boundaries of that existing city."  Um, but is
n't it time to expand a bit
?
But why?  What is the idea behind that, what would
be the taillight concept?
If Amsterdam doesn't have enough income,
but if you get money from land rent, it
would make sense to expand the land that
we can build on.
And then I think, then I see a cow like that and
then I smell the fertilizer and then I think:
"Why, why is this here?"  Yes.
And I don't understand that, because uh you
are against uh urban expansion.  Hmm hmm.
Generally speaking, right?  That, uh,
yeah, depends on which direction you go in when it
comes to business parks, so to speak;
then we look at it differently
.
But Greenfield, let's say outside the
building boundary, isn't in
principle, right?  Yes.   Yes.  Yes.
No, we really want to
protect greenery.
But I mean, it's not really green
in rural North, is it?  It is a
green color.   Yes.
Well, I do see the challenge we
have there, so to speak, to make
agriculture sustainable as well.  And
at the same time, it is an area that a great
many Amsterdammers
enjoy.
But of course, there is impism.
Then the alternative would be if we
build there, and you do it from the
perspective that you, as a municipality,
want to make a profit to invest in, for example, the
existing uh uh buildings,
then it means that you
are essentially just producing villas there.  And
then I think: "Yeah, which city are we
expanding then? Not Amsterdam, as far as
I know. Using housing more
efficiently does anyone else just to
say, 'Yes, fully, we're going to demolish, we're going to do demolition and
new construction,' to solve that sustainability challenge in one fell swoop
.
Yeah. Well, more efficient, maybe,
but at the same time I think—and
I find this really fantastic—about
Amsterdam's history. What I actually
learned much better only when
I became an alderman is that
various groups have actually blocked a
lot of these kinds of
plans over the years. And that is why
GroenLinks says: 'Let's be careful
with demolition and new construction, because then you
might also lose some very beautiful things
that you would like to keep.'"  Which is
exactly what we are so proud of.  I think, yes,
when you walk along the canals and see
the diversity of the homes, we are
also proud that it is all so old,
and yet we complain about ugly new builds
when they are in between.  if they
are 70s or 80s buildings.  Um, so yeah, we
should protect that city a little bit too
.  Also sometimes perhaps against
effectiveness.
What you actually see is that the more
highly educated a country becomes,
yes.   uh,
or a city, the more people will object
when something is built.  It is that when
people are highly educated and wealthy
, they get a sort of, uh,
English landed gentry mindset, and then
they want everything to stay quiet and the same.
Um, uh, and he said about
Rob Jette's 10 new cities plan
that it is the D6 voters who will be the
first to block it.  And
I thought that was a really funny one, but I
mean, that doesn't really matter.
Um, uh,
but the objection procedures, right? So that uh,
every time something gets built, then
uh, you get a uh,
then Femke Halsem has to go to some
uh community center where all these
people are standing around screaming.  Uh uh should
n't we just tell those people a bit harder, like,
your interests aren't
[music] first right now?   Hm.
It concerns the home seeker.   Yes.
No.  Yes.  Look, um, I think you're saying
a few things.  [music] Uh
first of all that um the democratic
right to participate.  Well, in my opinion, that is a
very important [music] asset.
Uh, I am a democrat, and I will
always defend that with heart [music] and tooth,
with uh uh everything that comes with it
.  On the other hand, yes, we
also see that that is just
getting really, um, out of hand and the whole system is grinding to a halt
because you
can undermine an entire process with every little trifle.  And this
actually has a bit to
do with what we
discussed previously regarding how you can set
permits, uh, and those
processes for [music] in motion in parallel.  Of
course, you could make that much simpler here as well
.  People must be able to have
their say, [music] must be able to have an opinion
about a neighborhood, about a
district.  In fact, I consider that a great
asset, and I find it so important that we should
actually move towards
giving home seekers a voice in
that process as well.  Um, that is why we in
Amsterdam as D60 said: "Now get
to work with a, uh, yes, with a council
or a group of home seekers
that you can consult the moment
you, uh, undertake new construction, [music] the
moment you start developing a neighborhood
, the moment you, uh, uh, start working on a
transformation, uh, uh, project."
Bram had
enough. [music] This all looked
hopeless and the system was unfair.
Everyone who hustled their way in on time
reaped the rewards at the expense of those on the
outside.
It seemed like a pyramid scheme—what if there was a
way to make it work for
everyone? Bram imagined a city of
glittering skyscrapers stretching
from rural north to southeast. Hell, screw
it. A city. Rotterdam, Utrecht, The
Hague, and Amsterdam would be integrated.
It would be a megalopolis bigger than London
and Paris, all achieved by leveraging
agglomeration effects [music] to
turbocharge housing production,
reasonable supply side deregulation, flying
cars—maybe not that high-speed
rail crossing, the Green Heart, a gradual
increase in the own  dwelling for fet
combined with the abolition of the
overdugsbasting in order to increase
flexibility
Bram would rule the ministry of spatial
planning by decree the canals would be
lit by biolumininess and algega
[music]
sy
hous pren market building amsterdam
would be grad harmonized inclusionary
zoning heavy industri sent to [music]
entirely new cafes and restaurants next
to residential housing the ministry of
housing would install edward glazer as
head of production the government would
se redistribution via rent  control and
allow rents in the regulated sector to
rise in order to improve the financial
position of corporations land rent
[music]
armiducam
jasper by Edward Frederik to dream of a
better world bram went to sleep he had
to be up early tomorrow to v
Hey yo, thank you for watching.  If it
wasn't clear that we don't really know
what we're talking about, I hope that
ending clears it up.  I wanted to say
thank you to the politicians for being
willing to do this.  Obviously, uh we're
not necessarily the most pleasant people
to do  these interviews with, but they
were good sports.  The full interviews
which are around an hour long are on my
new channel Russ.  We have a lot more
specific Dutch Jason content released
there with English subtitles.  I'm a
believer that municipal politics matters
much much more than people give credit
to.  So if you have some time interested
in moreance debates tribalism we see
today recommend watching them up to you
F.